Register of the Poland. Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych records,
1940-1945
47036
Poland. Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych
13 manuscript boxes (5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Essays, bulletins, reports, and studies, relating to Poland's boundary disputes following World Wars I and II; events and conditions in Poland under German and Soviet occupations during World War II; Polish-Soviet relations; communism in Poland; and twentieth century Polish agriculture, economy, foreign relations, history, politics, and government.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (16 reels).
Historical Note
Ministry of Preparatory Work Concerning the Peace Conference, Polish Government-in-Exile (London).
Scope and Content Note
The Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych was brought to life by the Presidential decree of July 1942. It had been known earlier, since 1940, as the Biuro Prac Politycznych, Ekonomicznych i Prawnych (Department of Political, Economic and Legal Analysis). The ministry's English name is self-explanatory: Ministry of Preparatory Work Concerning the Peace Conference.
Unlike other branches of the government it functioned more as an advisory agency by collecting ideas for the country's post-war political and economic reconstruction. Ideas were solicited from top class specialists, researchers, government experts, and non-government employees.
That was also a way for the ministry to provide financial support to those who found themselves out of work in exile but who could, thus, contribute to the government's information bank.
The materials included in this collection deal with some of the most critical issues for Poland, which should have been solved either during the war or shortly thereafter. They document how Poles envisioned their future and how little of those plans materialized between 1945 and 1989. But the researcher should remember that these are not official government plans but merely suggestions submitted for consideration.
Among the issues of particular importance discussed here are the restoration of the German state; Poland's relations with the Soviet Union; borders and historic disputes about them; and events and conditions in the country under Soviet and German occupation. Plans to restore the Polish economy and the problem of war reparations are particularly well covered.
Researchers are also advised to consult the Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych records, also in the Hoover Archives, on topics such as disarmament, execution of treaties, economic organization of post-war Europe, Central European federation, boundary disputes, and military and political alliances.
The records of the Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych were sent to the Hoover Institution in 1947 along with the archives of the Polish Research Centre (London).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Communism.; Communism--Poland.; Katyn Forest Massacre, 1940.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Poland.; Poland--Boundaries.; Poland--Economic conditions.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland--Politics and government--1918-1945.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.
Series Description
- Reports, 1940-1945. (Box 1-12)
  Reports, analyses, statistical data, submitted to the Ministerstwo Spraw Kongresowych, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Printed Matter, 1942-1944. (Box 13)
  Issues of Przeglad Literatury Politycznej, arranged chronologically
Container List
- REPORTS, 1940-1945 (Box 1)
  - General. List of the articles and publications of the Ministerstwo Spraw Kongresowych included in the collection (Folder 1: 1)
  - Agriculture - Economic aspects
    - Eastern Europe (Folder 1: 2)
    - Germany (Folder 1: 3)
    - Poland, 1945- (Folder 1: 4)
  - Allied Powers (1919- ). Reparation Commission - Poland (Folder 1: 5)
  - Atlantic Charter (1941) (Folder 1: 6)
  - Austria (Folder 1: 7)
  - Baltic Sea., See also National Security - Baltic States
    - General (Folder 1: 8)
    - Poland (Folder 1: 9)
  - Catholic Church - International law (Folder 1: 10)
  - Coal mines and mining - Poland
    - General
      - General (Folder 1: 11)
      - Export (Folder 1: 12)
    - German occupation (Folder 1: 13)
  - Czechoslovak-Polish Confederation (Proposed)
    - General (Folder 1: 14)
    - Economic cooperation (Folder 1: 15)
    - Maritime agreement (Folder 1: 16)
  - Disarmament - Germany
    - General (Folder 1: 17)
    - Chemical industry (Folder 1: 18)
  - Federalism (Box 2)
    - Central Europe
      - General
        - General (Folder 2: 1)
        - Plans, 1914-1939 (Folder 2: 2)
      - Agriculture (Folder 2: 3)
      - Economy
        - General (Folder 2: 4)
        - Import-export (Folder 2: 5)
        - Industrial development, British interest in (Folder 2: 6)
        - International cooperation (Folder 2: 7)
        - Need for capital (Folder 2: 8)
      - Merchant marine (Folder 2: 9)
      - Minerals (Folder 2: 10)
      - Population (Folder 2: 11)
      - Transport (Folder 2: 12)
    - North-Central Europe (Folder 2: 13)
    - South-Eastern Europe (Folder 2: 14)
  - Gdansk (Poland)
    - General (Folder 2: 15)
    - Economy (Folder 2: 16)
  - Industries
  - Industries
    - Central Europe - Steel (Folder 3: 1)
    - Germany
      - General, 1945- (Folder 3: 2)
      - Control of (Folder 3: 3)
      - De-industrialization of (Folder 3: 4)
      - Electricity production
        - Part 1 (Folder 3: 5)
        - Part 2
          - General (Folder 3: 6)
          - Enclosures (Folder 3: 7)
      - Foreign investments (Folder 3: 8)
      - Mining (Folder 3: 9)
      - Paper (Folder 3: 10)
      - Printing industries (Folder 3: 11)
      - Steel (Folder 3: 12)
    - Great Britain - Coal mines (Folder 3: 13)
    - Poland
      - Management, 1918-1944 (Folder 3: 14)
      - Ship building (Folder 3: 15)
      - Stone making (Folder 3: 16)
  - International trade - Europe (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Investments, Foreign - Poland (Folder 4: 2)
  - Jews - Poland (Folder 4: 3)
  - Labor (International law) (Folder 4: 4)
  - Latvia., See also Estonia (Folder 4: 5)
  - League of Nations
    - Part 1 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Part 2 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Part 3 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Lend-lease operations (1941-1945) - Soviet Union (Folder 4: 9)
  - Lithuanians., See Political refugees
  - Lumber trade
    - General (Folder 4: 10)
    - Central Europe (Folder 4: 11)
  - Merchant marine - International ownership regulations (Folder 4: 12)
  - Minorities
    - Germany - Repatriation of Poles (Folder 4: 13)
    - Poland (Box 5)
      - Germans
        - General (Folder 5: 1)
        - Optants (Folder 5: 2)
        - Property of (Folder 5: 3)
        - Resettlement, Post-war (Folder 5: 4)
      - Mazurzy (Folder 5: 5)
      - North-Eastern province (Folder 5: 6)
      - Ukrainians (Folder 5: 7)
    - Protection of (Folder 5: 8)
  - Munich Four-Power Agreement (1938) (Folder 5: 9)
  - National security
    - Baltic states
      - General (Folder 5: 10)
      - Russian interest in (Folder 5: 11)
    - Scandinavia., See Baltic States
  - Petroleum industry and trade - Poland (Folder 5: 12)
  - Poland
    - Boundaries., See also Treaty of Versailles (1919) and World War, 1939-1945 - Territorial questions - Poland
      - General
        - General (Folder 5: 13)
        - National self-determination and borders (Folder 5: 14)
      - Hungary and Romania (Folder 5: 15)
      - Lithuania (Folder 5: 16)
      - Slovakia (Folder 5: 17)
      - Soviet Union (Folder 5: 18)
    - Economic conditions (Box 6)
      - 1918-
        - General
          - Eastern provinces (Folder 6: 1)
          - Malopolska (Folder 6: 2)
        - International debt, 1936 (Folder 6: 3)
        - Cotton industry (Folder 6: 4)
        - Sea ports (Folder 6: 5)
      - War losses, 1939-1945
        - General
          - 1939-1940 (Folder 6: 6)
          - 1939-1941 (Folder 6: 7)
          - 1939-1944 (Folder 6: 8)
        - Commerce, 1939 (Folder 6: 9)
        - Forests and timber (Folder 6: 10)
        - Polskie Radio (Folder 6: 11)
        - Population (Folder 6: 12)
    - Economic policy - 1918-1945 - International agreements (Folder 6: 13)
    - Foreign relations
      - Germany (Folder 6: 14)
      - Lithuania (Folder 6: 15)
      - Soviet Union
        - General (Folder 6: 16)
        - 1921-1943 (Folder 6: 17)
        - 1939 (Folder 6: 18)
    - History
      - Occupation, 1939-1945
        - German
          - Administration (Folder 7: 1)
          - Eastern Poland (Folder 7: 2)
          - Economic exploitation (Folder 7: 3)
          - Forced labor (Folder 7: 4)
          - Germanization (Folder 7: 5)
          - Gross national product (Folder 7: 6)
          - Industrial policy (Folder 7: 7)
          - Legal system (Folder 7: 8)
          - Lublin region (Folder 7: 9)
          - Political system (Folder 7: 10)
          - Private property (Folder 7: 11)
        - Soviet - Eastern Poland
          - General (Folder 7: 12)
          - Deportations, 1939-1940 (Folder 7: 13)
          - Economic policy (Folder 7: 14)
          - Elections 1939 (Folder 7: 15)
          - Invasion, 1939 (Folder 7: 16)
    - Religion - National Evangelic Church (Folder 7: 17)
  - Poland. Rada Narodowa (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Poles
    - Poles (Folder 8: 2)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 8: 3)
  - Political refugees - Lithuanians (Folder 8: 4)
  - Public administration - Poland (Folder 8: 5)
  - Reconstruction (1939-1951)
    - General
      - Allied governments collaborating agencies (Folder 8: 6)
      - New world order (Folder 8: 7)
    - Germany (Folder 8: 8)
    - Great Britain. Merchant marine (Folder 8: 9)
    - Poland
      - General (Folder 8: 10)
      - Fiscal and credit policy (Folder 8: 11)
      - Foreign trade (Folder 8: 12)
      - Machinery needed (Folder 8: 13)
      - Resources (Folder 8: 14)
  - Riga, Treaty of, 1921 (Folder 8: 15)
  - River channels - Odra-Prosna-Warta (Folder 8: 16)
  - Romania (Folder 8: 17)
  - Silesia
    - General
      - Opole (Folder 8: 18)
      - Upper (Folder 8: 19)
    - Economy (Folder 8: 20)
    - History (Folder 8: 21)
    - Plebiscites (Folder 8: 22)
  - Slovaks - United States (Folder 8: 23)
  - Social security - Poland - World War, 1939-1945 (Folder 9: 1)
  - Soviet Union
    - Population (Folder 9: 2)
    - Religion (Folder 9: 3)
  - Transit, International - Europe - Congresses (Folder 9: 4)
  - Treaty of Versailles (1919)., See also Poland -Boundaries and World War, 1939-1945 - Territorial questions - Poland
    - General (Folder 9: 5)
    - Poland's borders
      - Eastern (Folder 9: 6)
      - Western (Folder 9: 7)
  - United States - Foreign relations - Soviet Union (Folder 9: 8)
  - World War, 1914-1918 - Reparations - France (Folder 9: 9)
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - Destruction and pillage (Folder 9: 10)
    - Economic aspects - Germany., See Industries - Germany
    - Equipment and supplies - Germany (Folder 9: 11)
    - Reparations
      - Germany (Folder 9: 12)
      - Great Britain - Legal aspects (Folder 9: 13)
      - Poland
        - General
          - General (Folder 9: 14)
          - Legal aspects (Folder 9: 15)
        - Agriculture (Folder 9: 16)
        - Automobile and motorcycle industry (Box-folder 10: 1)
        - Building materials (Folder 10: 2)
        - Chemical industry (Folder 10: 3)
        - Construction industry (Folder 10: 4)
        - Consumer goods (Folder 10: 5)
        - Cultural goods (Folder 10: 6)
        - Electric industry (Folder 10: 7)
        - Electrification (Folder 10: 8)
        - Fishing industry (Folder 10: 9)
        - Foundries (Folder 10: 10)
        - German labor contribution (Folder 10: 11)
        - Mining
          - General (Folder 10: 12)
          - Inventory of losses
            - Part 1 (Folder 10: 13)
            - Part 2 (Folder 10: 14)
        - Municipal services (Folder 10: 15)
        - Municipal transport (Folder 10: 16)
        - Oil industry (Folder 10: 17)
        - Port equipment (Folder 11: 1)
        - Precision mechanics and optics (Folder 11: 2)
        - River regulation (Folder 11: 3)
        - Sport (Folder 11: 4)
        - Steel works (Folder 11: 5)
        - Telecommunication (Folder 11: 6)
        - Textile industry (Folder 11: 7)
        - Transport
          - General (Folder 11: 8)
          - Air (Folder 11: 9)
          - Railroad equipment (Folder 11: 10)
          - Sea (Folder 11: 11)
        - Water supply and sewers (Folder 11: 12)
        - Wood (Folder 11: 13)
    - Territorial questions - Poland., See also Poland - Boundaries and Treaty of Versailles (1919) (Box 12)
      - East
        - General
          - General (Folder 12: 1)
          - Annexation (Folder 12: 2)
          - Conflict over (Folder 12: 3)
          - Curzon line (Folder 12: 4)
          - Provinces (Folder 12: 5)
        - East Prussia
          - General (Folder 12: 6)
          - Property estimate (Folder 12: 7)
      - West
        - General (Folder 12: 8)
        - Szczecin, Brandenburg and Pomerania (Folder 12: 9)
    - Treaties
      - Germany - Revision (Folder 12: 10)
      - International - Postwar (Folder 12: 11)
    - United States. Dept. of the Treasury - Management, 1940s (Folder 12: 12)
    - War aims
      - Great Britain (Folder 12: 13)
      - Poland (Folder 12: 14)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1942-1944. (Box 13)
  Issues of Przeglad Literatury Politycznej
  - 1942 April-December (Folder 13: 1)
  - 1943
    - February-June (Folder 13: 2)
    - July-December (Folder 13: 3)
  - 1944 March-December (Folder 13: 4)